Translator: Morton Bast Reviewer: Thu-Huong Ha
번역: Keewoo Lee 검토: Surie Lee
Let me tell you a story.
이야기 하나 들려 드릴게요.
It's my first year as a new high school science teacher,
고등학교 과학 교사로 부임한 첫 해였습니다.
and I'm so eager.
저는 열정에 가득차 있었죠,
I'm so excited, I'm pouring myself into my lesson plans.
너무 흥분되었고 수업 계획을 만드는 데에 몰두했죠.
But I'm slowly coming to this horrifying realization
그런데 점점 끔직한 사실을 알게 되었어요.
that my students just might not be learning anything.
어쩌면 제 학생들이 아무것도 배우지 못할거라는 것이었습니다.
This happens one day:
어느 날의 일이었어요.
I'd just assigned my class to read this textbook chapter
학생들에게 교과서 한 단원을 읽어오라고 숙제를 냈습니다.
about my favorite subject in all of biology:
생물학 전체에서 제가 가장 좋아하는 부분인
viruses and how they attack.
바이러스와 그것들이 어떻게 공격하는지에 대해서 말이죠.
And so I'm so excited to discuss this with them,
그리고 저는 학생들과 그것에 대해 이야기할 생각에 들떠서
and I come in and I say, "Can somebody please explain
수업에 들어가자마자 물었습니다. "누가 책의 주제와
the main ideas and why this is so cool?"
그것이 왜 그렇게 멋진지 말해볼래?"
There's silence.
아무도 대답하지 않았어요.
Finally, my favorite student, she looks me straight in the eye,
마침내, 제가 제일 좋아하는 학생이 제 눈을 똑바로 쳐다보고선,
and she says, "The reading sucked."
"더럽게 재미없었어요" 라더군요.
And then she clarified. She said, "You know what,
그리고나서 말하더군요, "사실은 말이죠,
I don't mean that it sucks. It means that I didn't understand a word of it.
더럽게 재미없었단 것은 아니에요. 단 한 구절도 이해를 못하겠다는 뜻이었어요.
It's boring. Um, who cares, and it sucks."
지루했어요. 어쨋든 더럽게 재미없었어요."
These sympathetic smiles
지금 이 동정어린 미소들이
spread all throughout the room now,
교실 전체로 퍼졌습니다.
and I realize that all of my other students are in the same boat,
그리고 저는 모든 학생들이 같은 상황에 있다는 것을 깨달았어요,
that maybe they took notes or they memorized definitions from the textbook,
그들은 아마 필기도 하고 교과서에있는 정의들도 암기했겠지만,
but not one of them really understood the main ideas.
단 한명도 주제를 이해하지 못했다는 것도요,
Not one of them can tell me why this stuff is so cool,
단 한명도 왜 이것이 그렇게 멋진 것인지 말할 수 없었습니다.
why it's so important.
왜 그것이 중요한지도 말이죠.
I'm totally clueless.
어찌해야 할지 몰르겠더군요.
I have no idea what to do next.
다음에 무엇을 해야할지 전혀 감이 안 왔어요
So the only thing I can think of is say,
제가 유일하게 할 수 있는 것은 이렇게 말하는 것이었죠.
"Listen. Let me tell you a story.
"자, 이야기 하나를 들려줄게요
The main characters in the story are bacteria and viruses.
이야기의 주인공들은 박테리아와 바이러스에요.
These guys are blown up a couple million times.
이것들은 200만 배나 확대된 것들이죠
The real bacteria and viruses are so small
실제 박테리아와 바이러스는 너무 작아서
we can't see them without a microscope,
현미경 없이는 볼 수 없어요.
and you guys might know bacteria and viruses
그리고 여러분은 박테리아와 바이러스를 알고 있을 거에요.
because they both make us sick.
왜냐하면 둘 다 우리를 병들게 하니까요.
But what a lot of people don't know is that viruses
하지만 많은 사람들은 모릅니다.
can also make bacteria sick."
바이러스도 박테리아를 병들게 할 수 있다는 것을요."
Now, the story that I start telling my kids,
제가 제 학생들에게 들려주기 시작한 이야기는
it starts out like a horror story.
무서운 이야기처럼 시작됩니다.
Once upon a time there's this happy little bacterium.
아주 먼 옛날, 행복한 작은 박테리아가 살았어요.
Don't get too attached to him.
너무 중요하게 생각하지는 마세요.
Maybe he's floating around in your stomach
어쩌면 그 사람은 그저 여러분의 장을 떠돌거나
or in some spoiled food somewhere,
상한 음식 어딘가에 있을 수도 있어요.
and all of a sudden he starts to not feel so good.
그리고 갑자기 그 사람은 몸이 안좋아지기 시작하죠.
Maybe he ate something bad for lunch,
아마 점심에 상한 것을 먹었나봐요.
and then things get really horrible,
그리고 갑자기 끔찍한 일이 벌어집니다.
as his skin rips apart, and he sees a virus
그의 피부가 벗겨져 나가고,
coming out from his insides.
몸안에서 바이러스가 나오는 것을 보게됩니다.
And then it gets horrible
그리고 더 끔찍한 것은
when he bursts open and an army of viruses
그 사람이 완전히 터져버리고 바이러스 한 부대가
floods out from his insides.
그 사람의 안에서 넘쳐나오는 겁니다.
If -- Ouch is right! --
만약 -- 맞아요, "아야" --
If you see this, and you're a bacterium,
만약 여러분들이 이 장면을 보았다면, 그리고 여러분이 박테리아라면
this is like your worst nightmare.
이건 최악의 악몽이겠죠,
But if you're a virus and you see this,
하지만 여러분이 바이러스이고, 이 장면을 본다면
you cross those little legs of yours and you think,
여러분들은 짧은 다리를 꼬며 생각하겠죠
"We rock."
"우리가 최고야"
Because it took a lot of crafty work to infect this bacterium.
왜냐하면 이 박테리아를 감염시키기 위해 많은 작업이 필요했기 때문이에요.
Here's what had to happen.
이제 어떤 일이 벌어졌었는지 봅시다.
A virus grabbed onto a bacterium
바이러스가 박테리아 위에 올라타서는
and it slipped its DNA into it.
자신의 DNA를 슬쩍 집어 넣죠.
The next thing is, that virus DNA made stuff
다음으로, 바이러스의 DNA는
that chopped up the bacteria DNA.
박테리아의 DNA를 잘게 부숴버릴 물질을 만들죠.
And now that we've gotten rid of the bacteria DNA,
그리고 이제 박테리아 DNA를 해치웠습니다.
the virus DNA takes control of the cell
바이러스 DNA가 세포를 조종하게 됩니다
and it tells it to start making more viruses.
그리고 그 DNA는 세포가 더 많은 바이러스를 만들게하기 시작하죠.
Because, you see, DNA is like a blueprint
DNA는 생명체에게 무엇을 만들지 말해주는
that tells living things what to make.
청사진과 같기 때문이에요.
So this is kind of like going into a car factory
이것은 마치 자동차 공장에 들어가서
and replacing the blueprints with blueprints for killer robots.
살인 기계를 만드는 청사진으로 바꾸는 것과 같아요.
The workers still come the next day, they do their job,
작업자들은 다음 날에 와서 여전히 그들의 일을 합니다.
but they're following different instructions.
하지만 그들은 다른 지침을 따르고 있는거죠.
So replacing the bacteria DNA with virus DNA
그래서 DNA 바이러스와 박테리아 DNA를 교체하는 것은
turns the bacteria into a factory for making viruses --
바이러스를 만들기 위한 공장으로 박테리아를 바꾸는 거에요.
that is, until it's so filled with viruses that it bursts.
즉, 바이러스가 가득 차서 터져버릴 때까지 말이죠.
But that's not the only way that viruses infect bacteria.
하지만 이것이 바이러스가 박테리아를 감염시키는 유일한 방법은 아닙니다.
Some are much more crafty.
어떤 것은 훨씬 더 교활합니다.
When a secret agent virus infects a bacterium,
비밀 요원 바이러스가 박테리아를 감염시킬 때,
they do a little espionage.
그들은 작은 스파이 행위를 합니다.
Here, this cloaked, secret agent virus is slipping his DNA into the bacterial cell,
여기 이 변장한 비밀 요원 바이러스는 박테리아 세포에 자신의 DNA를 넣고 있습니다,
but here's the kicker: It doesn't do anything harmful -- not at first.
여기에 첫번째 선수가 있습니다. 아무런 해를 끼치지 않아요 -- 처음에는 말이죠.
Instead, it silently slips into the bacteria's own DNA,
대신에 그것은 박테리아의 DNA로 미끄러져 들어가죠.
and it just stays there like a terrorist sleeper cell,
그리고는 가만히 그곳에서 기다려요. 마치 잠복해있는 테러리스트처럼 말이에요.
waiting for instructions.
지시를 기다리면서요.
And what's interesting about this is now whenever this bacteria has babies,
그리고 여기서 흥미로운 것은 박테리아가 아기를 가질 때에
the babies also have the virus DNA in them.
아기들 또한 바이러스 DNA를 그들 안에 가지고 있다는 것입니다.
So now we have a whole extended bacteria family,
그래서 이제 우리는 확장된 박테리아 가족을 보게 되는거에요.
filled with virus sleeper cells.
잠자는 바이러스로 가득 채워지는거죠.
They're just happily living together until a signal happens
그들은 그저 행복하게 함께 삽니다. 신호가 나타나기 전까지는요.
and -- BAM! -- all of the DNA pops out.
그리고선 -- 빵! -- 모든 DNA가 밖으로 튀어 나옵니다.
It takes control of these cells, turns them into virus-making factories,
DNA는 세포들을 지배하고, 그들을 바이러스 공장으로 만들죠.
and they all burst,
그리고는 그들 모두가 터져버립니다.
a huge, extended bacteria family,
하나의 커다란 확장된 박테리아 가족은
all dying with viruses spilling out of their guts,
모두 그들의 내장에서 바이러스들을 쏟아내면서 죽습니다.
the viruses taking over the bacterium.
바이러스가 박테리아를 탈취하면서 말이죠.
So now you understand how viruses can attack cells.
이제 여러분들은 바이러스가 세포를 어떻게 공격하는지 이해했습니다.
There are two ways: On the left is what we call the lytic way,
두가지 방법이 있죠 왼쪽은 용균적 방법이라고 부릅니다.
where the viruses go right in and take over the cells.
바이러스가 바로 들어가서 세포를 차지하는 방법이죠.
On the [right] is the lysogenic way
오른쪽은 용원적 방법이라고 부릅니다.
that uses secret agent viruses.
비밀 요원 바이러스를 사용하는 방법이죠.
So this stuff is not that hard, right?
아주 어렵지는 않죠?
And now all of you understand it.
그리고 지금 여러분 모두 이것을 이해했어요.
But if you've graduated from high school,
그런데 여러분이 고등학교를 졸업했다면,
I can almost guarantee you've seen this information before.
이런 내용에 대해 분명 본 적이 있을 거에요.
But I bet it was presented in a way
하지만 여러분들의 머리에 들어갈 수 없는
that it didn't exactly stick in your mind.
방식으로 배웠을 것입니다.
So when my students were first learning this,
제 학생들이 이 내용을 처음 배울 때에는
why did they hate it so much?
왜 그렇게 싫어했을까요?
Well, there were a couple of reasons.
자, 몇가지 이유가 있죠.
First of all, I can guarantee you that their textbooks
무엇보다 먼저, 학생들이 보는 교과서는
didn't have secret agent viruses, and they didn't have horror stories.
비밀 요원 바이러스도, 무서운 이야기도 없어요.
You know, in the communication of science
아시다시피, 과학의 세계에서는
there is this obsession with seriousness.
진지함에 집착하는 경향이 있습니다.
It kills me. I'm not kidding.
그게 저를 정말 힘들게 합니다. 농담이 아니에요.
I used to work for an educational publisher,
전에 교과서 저자로 일한 적이 있는데요.
and as a writer, I was always told never to use stories
항상 절대 이야기나 재밌는 말을
or fun, engaging language,
사용하지 않도록 당부받았죠.
because then my work might not be viewed
왜냐하면 그렇게 되면 제 작품이
as "serious" and "scientific."
"진지하게" 혹은 "과학적으로" 보이지 않기 때문이랍니다.
Right? I mean, because God forbid somebody have fun
맞아요? 그러니까, 하느님이 우리가 재미있어하는 것을 금지했기 때문이라는겁니다.
when they're learning science.
우리가 과학을 배울 때 말이죠.
So we have this field of science that's all about slime,
이런 교묘한 이야기와 같은 과학 분야도 있는데 말이에요.
and color changes. Check this out.
그리고 색 변화같은 것들도 있구요. 이걸 보세요.
And then we have, of course, as any good scientist has to have,
그리고 많은 과학자들에게와 마찬가지로 우리에게는 이런 것도 있죠.
explosions!
폭발!
But if a textbook seems too much fun,
하지만 교과서가 너무 재미있으면,
it's somehow unscientific.
어떤 면에서 비과학적으로 보입니다.
Now another problem was that
또 다른 문제는
the language in their textbook was truly incomprehensible.
교과서에 쓰인 말들은 정말 이해할 수 없어요.
If we want to summarize that story that I told you earlier,
만약 우리가 방금 제가 들려드린 이야기를 요약하고 싶다면,
we could start by saying something like,
우리는 이렇게 시작할 수 있을 겁니다.
"These viruses make copies of themselves
"바이러스들은 DNA를 박테리아에
by slipping their DNA into a bacterium."
주입시켜 자신을 복제한다."
The way this showed up in the textbook, it looked like this:
교과서에서 나타난 방식은 이렇습니다.
"Bacteriophage replication is initiated
"살균 바이러스의 자가 복제는
through the introduction of viral nucleic acid
박테리아에 바이러스 핵산이 주입되면서
into a bacterium."
시작된다"
That's great, perfect for 13-year-olds.
13살 학생들에게 참 좋은 설명 방식이죠?
But here's the thing. There are plenty of people
하지만 여기에는 문제가 있습니다. 과학 교육계의
in science education who would look at this and say there's no way
매우 많은 사람들이 이걸 보고 이렇게 말하죠.
that we could ever give that to students,
정확하지 않은 언어를 포함하기 때문에
because it contains some language that isn't completely accurate.
학생들에게 가르칠 수 없다고요.
For example, I told you that viruses have DNA.
예를 들어, 저는 바이러스가 DNA를 가지고 있다고 말했습니다.
Well, a very tiny fraction of them don't.
그런데 소수는 그렇지 않습니다.
They have something called RNA instead.
그들은 대신에 RNA라는 것을 가지고 있죠.
So a professional science writer would circle that
전문적인 과학 작가는 여기에 동그라미를 치고
and say, "That has to go.
말하겠죠, "이건 좀 손봐야겠는데"
We have to change it to something much more technical."
훨씬 더 전문적으로 바꿔야겠어"
And after a team of professional science editors
과학 서적 편집자들이
went over this really simple explanation,
이 정말 간단한 설명을 다 읽은 후에는
they'd find fault with almost every word I've used,
제가 사용한 거의 모든 단어에 문제를 제기할 것입니다.
and they'd have to change anything that wasn't serious enough,
그리고 그들은 충분히 진지하지 않은 것들을 모두 바꾸겠죠.
and they'd have to change everything
그리고 100% 완벽하지 않으면
that wasn't 100 percent perfect.
모두 바꿔 버릴 것입니다.
Then it would be accurate,
그렇게 되면, 정확해지겠죠.
but it would be completely impossible to understand.
하지만 그렇게 되면 이해할 수 없는 말들이 될거에요.
This is horrifying.
그건 정말 끔찍합니다.
You know, I keep talking about this idea
저는 이야기를 들려주어야 한다는
of telling a story,
생각을 계속 주장해왔지만,
and it's like science communication has taken on this idea
과학적 소통의 방법이 이런 생각을 억압한 것과 같습니다.
of what I call the tyranny of precision,
저는 이것을 "정확성의 억압"이라고 부르죠.
where you can't just tell a story.
마음대로 이야기를 들려줄 수가 없어요.
It's like science has become that horrible storyteller
그건 마치 과학이 끔찍하게 모자란 이야기꾼이 되어버린것 같아요.
that we all know, who gives us all the details nobody cares about,
아무도 관심 없는 사소한 모든 것에 대해 말하주는 이야기꾼 말입니다.
where you're like, "Oh, I met my friend for lunch the other day,
마치 "내가 친구랑 점심에 만났는데,
and she was wearing these ugly jeans.
그녀가 별로 예쁘지 않은 청바지를 입고 있었어.
I mean, they weren't really jeans, they were more kind of, like, leggings,
아 근데 사실 청바지는 아니었어. 음 일종의 레깅스 비슷했어,
but, like, I guess they're actually kind of more like jeggings,
음, 그런데, 내가 보기에 제깅스 같기도 했어.
like, but I think — " and you're just like, "Oh my God.
아 근데......" 당신은 이러겠죠, "아 제발!
What is the point?"
그래서 뭘 얘기하고 싶은건데?"
Or even worse, science education is becoming
끔찍한 것은 과학 교육이
like that guy who always says, "Actually."
방금 그 사람처럼 되어간다는 것입니다.
Right? You want to be like, "Oh, dude,
그렇죠? 여러분이 다음과 같이 얘기한다고 해 봅시다.
we had to get up in the middle of the night
"우리 그때 한밤중에 일어나서
and drive a hundred miles in total darkness."
칠흑같은 어둠에서 160 킬로미터를 운전해야 했었지.. "
And that guy's like, "Actually, it was 87.3 miles."
그러면 그 사람은, "사실, 81.3 킬로미터었어"
And you're like, "Actually, shut up!
그러면 여러분은 "입닥쳐!
I'm just trying to tell a story."
난 그냥 이야기를 하려고 한거잖아." 하시겠죠.
Because good storytelling is all about emotional connection.
좋은 이야기에는 감정 전달이 매우 중요하기 때문에
We have to convince our audience
우리는 청중을 몰입시켜야합니다.
that what we're talking about matters.
우리가 무엇을 말하려는지에 대해서 말이죠.
But just as important is knowing
하지만 어떤 사소한 것들을,
which details we should leave out
요점을 말하기 위해
so that the main point still comes across.
무엇을 무시할 것인지도 중요합니다.
I'm reminded of what the architect Mies van der Rohe said,
건축가 미스 반 데 로에(Mies van der Rohe)가 한 말이 생각나네요.
and I paraphrase, when he said that sometimes
그가 "가끔 진실을 말하기 위해서는
you have to lie in order to tell the truth.
거짓말을 해야할 때도 있다"라고 말했을 때
I think this sentiment is particularly relevant
저는 이 말이 특히 과학 교육과
to science education.
관련이 있다고 생각합니다.
Now, finally,
그리고 마지막으로
I am often so disappointed
저는 종종 실망합니다.
when people think that I'm advocating
사람들이 제가 과학의 수준을
a dumbing down of science.
낮추는 데 앞장 선다고 말할 때 말이죠.
That's not true at all.
그건 전혀 사실이 아니에요.
I'm currently a Ph.D. student at MIT,
저는 현재 MIT에서 박사과정을 밟고 있고,
and I absolutely understand the importance of detailed,
그리고 사소하고 자세한 것들과
specific scientific communication between experts,
전문가들 사이에서 쓰는 과학 용어들의 중요성도 아주 잘 알고있습니다.
but not when we're trying to teach 13-year-olds.
하지만 13살 짜리 애들을 가르칠 때에는 아니라는 거죠.
If a young learner thinks that all viruses have DNA,
만약 어린 학생이 모든 바이러스가 DNA를 가지고 있다고 생각한다고 해서
that's not going to ruin their chances of success in science.
그것이 과학적 성취의 기회를 가로막지는 않습니다.
But if a young learner can't understand anything in science
하지만 만약 어린 학생이 과학에 대해 아무것도 이해를 하지 못하고
and learns to hate it because it all sounds like this,
모두 이런 설명이라서 과학을 싫어한다면
that will ruin their chances of success.
그것은 과학적 성취의 기회를 가로막을 것입니다.
This needs to stop,
이런 것은 멈춰야만 합니다.
and I wish that the change could come from the institutions
저는 기관들에서 변화가 왔으면 좋겠습니다.
at the top that are perpetuating these problems,
앞에서 나온 이런 문제들을 영속시키는 기관들 말이에요.
and I beg them, I beseech them to just stop it.
그리고 애원합니다. 제발 그만하자고 간청합니다.
But I think that's unlikely.
하지만 제 생각에 그럴 가능성은 매우 낮아요.
So we are so lucky that we have resources
우리는 이런 이상한 교육을 피해 갈 수 있는
like the Internet, where we can circumvent these institutions
인터넷 같은 방법을 가지고 있어서
from the bottom up.
참 다행이에요.
There's a growing number of online resources
과학을 이해시키는 데에 최선을 다하는
that are dedicated to just explaining science
온라인 자료들이 점점 늘어나고 있습니다.
in simple, understandable ways.
간단하고 이해할 수 있는 방법으로 말이에요.
I dream of a Wikipedia-like website that would explain
저는 위키피디아와 같은 웹사이트를 꿈꿉니다.
any scientific concept you can think of
중학생들이 이해할 수 있는 쉬운 언어로
in simple language any middle schooler can understand.
생각할 수 있는 모든 과학적개념을 설명해 놓은 곳 말이에요.
And I myself spend most of my free time
그리고 저 스스로도 거의 모든 자유시간을
making these science videos that I put on YouTube.
유투브에 올리는 과학 동영상을 만들면서 보내죠.
I explain chemical equilibrium using analogies
화학 평형에 대한 개념을
to awkward middle school dances,
이상한 중학교 춤에 비유해서 설명하고
and I talk about fuel cells with stories
여름 캠프에서의 남자와 여자들의 이야기로
about boys and girls at a summer camp.
연료 전지에 대해서 이야기합니다.
The feedback that I get is sometimes misspelled
제가 받는 피드백들은 가끔 맞춤법이 틀리기도 하고
and it's often written in LOLcats,
종종 인터넷 속어로 적혀있기도 하죠
but nonetheless
하지만 그럼에도 불구하고
it's so appreciative, so thankful
과학을 소통해야 한다는 것이,
that I know this is the right way
올바른 길이라는 것을 제가 안다는 것이
we should be communicating science.
너무 고맙고, 감사한 일입니다.
There's still so much work left to be done, though,
그러나, 아직도 해야할 일들이 많이 남아있습니다.
and if you're involved with science in any way
만약 여러분들이 어떻게든지 과학과 관련된 일을 한다면
I urge you to join me.
저와 함께하시기를 권유합니다.
Pick up a camera, start to write a blog, whatever,
사진을 찍고, 블로그에 글을 쓰기 시작하든지 아무것이나 좋습니다.
but leave out the seriousness, leave out the jargon.
하지만 진지함은 던져버리세요. 전문 용어도 던져버리세요.
Make me laugh. Make me care.
웃게해 주세요. 관심을 가지게 만들어 주세요.
Leave out those annoying details that nobody cares about
아무도 신경쓰지 않는 사소한 것들도 던져버리세요.
and just get to the point.
핵심을 얘기하세요.
How should you start?
어떻게 시작해야 하냐고요?
Why don't you say, "Listen, let me tell you a story"?
그냥 말해보세요 "이야기를 하나 들려드릴요."
Thank you.
감사합니다.
(Applause)
(박수)